Yeah, I always get very mixed results
with those plant identification apps.
It's saying a Chickasaw plum,
but earlier it was saying it was a cherry plum
I've only seen one of them here.
And there are other, like, European plums.
Two of them close to the Land Rover
and one in front of the house.
And none of them give fruit.
Only on the one there I've seen
one little plum some years ago.
That could be a few reasons, actually.
There's not enough trees for cross
pollination
or the trees
are not compatible with each other.
Or too far out?
Too far away from each other.
And that could be the case.
They need to be pruned.
Some of them.
So this one I could prune.
I mean, it's doing beautifully,
but it grew very tall.
Because
it was all the old birches around it.
So they're all fighting for the light.
So they'll do better now,
but they need to be pruned.
But I think also a big reason
for no pollination
is that the bees are not here yet.
We're at 1200 meters, so it's quite cold.
These trees are blossoming
now in April,
but the bees kind of arrive in May.
When it warms up a bit more,
because I saw a few last week
when it was quite warm and sunny.
And the bumblebee is already here,
but just a few.
And this is a cold day.
It's like seven degrees Celsius.
So they,
they don't get out.
So that could also be
the reason that bees are too late.
But, you know,
we'll see. The apple trees...
those have been doing well,
but they're also very small yet.
So I think I'm going to pinch some flowers
because it was very heavy with apples
last year, which is great.
But the tree needs some time to grow.
So yeah, there is another pear tree.
I should make an overview of all
the fruit trees that are actually here.
And do some pruning before winter
and plant a few more, let them grow, and
see in a few years
how they are doing.
Work.
This is going to be the last stone.
That is going to go in the building,
the very last one.
Then it is finished,
almost a year of building.
The first stone, this one,
was laid in, I think, mid-May last year.
The foundation was done in November 2024.
And we had a long winter break.
So we did the floor, I think, late
April last year and then started the walls in May,
all summer laying stone until
about October I started building the scaffolding,
mid-October.
The beams went in in November, I think.
And then the roof was built
in the winter. So...
It's been a good run.
It might be interesting to do some calculations of how
how heavy this little building actually is,
because I think it's quite a lot.
Okay.
I’ve calculated the weight of the foundation,
the floor, walls, and the roof using AI.
So I've put in all the dimensions
I mentioned,
dimensions of the window,
dimensions of the lintels.
Also photos of how the wall is built.
It's still a rough estimation, but
to kind of see how much mortar is used
and how much stone.
So concrete foundation:
it's almost 17,000 kg.
I put the numbers here in pounds.
Floor slab:
a little over 10,000 kg,
the walls about 30... 31,000 kg.
Roof:
this is just the stones,
not the wood.
6.7, close to 7,000.
And then the wood.
I didn't calculate this,
but I guess that's about 3,000 kilos.
The total:
64,430 kg
and 142,000 pounds.
And then to think that every stone
is picked up twice or three times,
once to collect it, sort things out,
and then to pick it up, put it in the wall.
It's a lot! But it has been fun.
It might be interesting
to also do the calculation of the costs,
how much it costs, but I'll do that
after I've done electricity
and everything.
It costs less than it weighs,
for sure.
One of.
The underbody shield was bent after being stuck in the snow many times.
Do you want to go outside?
It’s their first time outside.
A bit hesitant, still.
But it’s greening up,
so it's nice for them to eat,
eat grass and all kinds of things.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm making good progress with the walls.
That pointing machine is just,
it goes so fast.
Not only fast,
it also goes really deep inside the wall.
So it really fills up the joints.
Next week we'll finish that up
because I have some help.
It’s better to do it with two people.
So one mixing and also stirring the bucket,
because you want to have like a
not too liquid mix, firm enough.
But then for the pump to be able to handle
it, it needs to be stirred all the time.
So a second person is needed to do it well.
And maybe we'll also do the floor.
I'm going to do
self-leveling screed,
a cement product,
not just normal cement, but
like a liquid cement
which is made for it.
And it'll make a nice floor.
And after that, I can put stuff inside.
But before I get machines in, I think I should work on the soil.
So there’s...
I see the concrete is slightly
damp in the corners.
It's not too bad, but you can
see that the foundation is getting wet.
At the back,
I need to dig out the hill a bit more.
So do some soil
work and put in some drainage as well
so it stays...
The humidity needs to be quite low
in the summer.
That's more difficult here.
And also, I need...
yeah, there’s quite a bit of digging work to do.
I need to update the solar panels.
I need to dig in a new line
towards the workshop
because I need two groups there.
Hey, guys.
Those are bilberries.
They’re not ripe yet.
Yeah, I'm
going to replace the solar panels and
run two new [electrical] groups towards the workshop.
In the beginning, I didn't think so big.
I didn't know I was going to be with Ela.
I didn't know I was going to build
a workshop for woodworking with machines.
So I'm expanding a bit.
But yeah.
Beautiful days...
I'm taking my time with the garden beds
because it's heavy work for my back.
The rotation with the shoveling.
I have to take that slow
because I feel it.
All the other work is okay,
but that is the worst work,
so it takes time.
Come back!